If they do go ahead with a coup, the
first step will be to take out Maduro.
There's been reports that Maduro was
seeking amnesty for the US for him to
step down. And Trump refused to give him
amnesty. If the US government is serious
about attacking a country, always watch
for naval movements. This was something
I learned early on at the CIA. And sure
enough, we sent the USS Gerald R. Ford
and its associated 11 battleships and
supply ships. And I said, "Oh, dang it.
The CIA used drugs as a way to weaken
other countries. The the drugs that are
in Venezuela are not Venezuelan. They
come from Colombia and they come from
Ecuador and they're transiting Venezuela
on their way to West Africa. Nothing
good comes from this kind of US foreign
policy. What do you expect to happen in
Venezuela if Maduro does step down?
>> Chaos.
>> Well, who thought who thought we'd be
talking about Venezuela today? We've
talked about Iran, we've talked about
Russia, Ukraine, we've talked about
China, and now Venezuela is in the mix.
>> What do you What's your initial
reaction? I was listening to you earlier
talk give a ask audience questions about
it. What's your initial reaction when
you started seeing that narrative shift?
Because you've seen that playbook
before. So, what was your first thought?
Well, you know, I've said many times
over the years that if you want to know
if the US government is serious about
attacking a country, always watch for
naval movements. This was something I
learned early on at the CIA that if if
we're really going to attack a country,
we need aircraft carrier battle groups
in place. So, I said a month ago or so,
I said, "We're not going to attack
Venezuela because we haven't sent an
aircraft carrier battle group." And sure
enough, we sent the USS Gerald R. Ford
and its associated 11 battleships and
supply ships. And I said, "Oh, dang it.
Now we're serious." At the same time
though, Mario, you know, you have to
look at what the upside is for the
United States. And I'm not seeing an
upside.
>> We're We're not at war with Venezuela.
we have made a policy decision to not
buy Venezuelan oil and to not refine
Venezuelan oil anymore. Um, so I don't
see what the upside to this is. You
would think that if if the
administration uh wants to get rid of
Venezuelan refugees or Venezuelan
immigrants, it would want to actually
strengthen the economy of Venezuela and
encourage them to go back. But that's
really not what we're seeing. So this
from a policy perspective, this doesn't
make much sense to me. And and you know
what, let me add two other things. One
is drugs. We're we're hearing a lot a
lot in the United States about
Venezuelan drugs. The the drugs that are
in Venezuela are not Venezuelan. They
come from Colombia and they come from
Ecuador and they're transiting Venezuela
on their way to West Africa where
they're then put on camels and taken up
this ancient Tuar uh dirt path to
Morocco where they're put on boats and
sent to Spain that these drugs are meant
for for Western Europe, not for the
United States. And finally, I think that
I think really what we're seeing here is
a slow motion response or a delayed
response to China's decision five years
ago to build uh an oil refinery in the
Caribbean. And the reason I say that is
Venezuela has very very dirty oil. They
have an ocean of it, but it's very high
in sulfur content and it needs it needs
significant um uh chemical
um distillation
>> refining
>> refining to not Yeah. And you can't even
use it to turn into gasoline for your
cars. It's mostly made into home heating
oil because it's so dirty and high in
sulfur. Well, until just five or six
years ago, the only place that you could
refine that oil was in Houston, Texas.
We built refineries that were
specialized just to handle Venezuelan
oil. But then of course we sanctioned
the Venezuelan oil industry. Well, the
Venezuelans didn't then just shut down
their oil industry. The Indians and the
Chinese built new refineries to handle
Venezuelan oil and they shipped the oil
there. The Chinese are swimming in
money. And so they decided instead of
shipping the Venezuelan oil all the way
to China, they'll just build the
refinery in the Caribbean, refine it
right there, and ship it out from the
Caribbean. And the United States doesn't
like that. So the bottom line here, I
think, is China, but Maduro's already
offered Trump a while ago, well before
the buildup, um, full access for the US
for Venezuelan oil. Because for Maduro,
it doesn't really care. He doesn't
really care where the money's coming
from. At the end of the day, his main
concern is regime survival. So, I just
don't see like if this that would be a
valid concern. We're seeing China expand
becoming the biggest trading partner for
many Latin American countries.
>> But I just don't see that to be a
solution for that. Like you don't you
don't go and and and and conduct a
regime change operation because a
country is doing more business with
another country. So that's that's why I
like your point because you started off
saying that you look at naval movements
to see if that if the US is serious
about a certain country and taking
military action in a country including
regime change and we saw that recently
in the Middle East. Um but you also said
that it just does not make strategic
sense for a regime change in Venezuela
for such a a large large country even
though Maduro is not that popular in the
country and you've said that previously
you know like me you don't like Maduro.
I don't like Maduro. Um
your your first point though, how likely
is it for naval movements like this to
happen as a bluff by the US as a
negotiating tactic by Trump to try to
force
>> Oh, sure. Sure. We we do this all the
time in the South China Sea. Uh so yeah,
it very well could be a bluff just to
make him jump on a plane and run away.
That would be as far as US policy, that
would probably be the the preferred end
to this thing. just had to have him get
on a plane and fly to Havana or Moscow
or somewhere else where he can live
happily ever after. Uh but then again,
it leaves a power vacuum. There are
multiple right-wing factions. There's
the there's the military which is pro
Maduro. So, we don't have any idea what
the military would intend to do. I I
just again I just don't see an upside to
this. And then on top of all that, when
you have all of the region's powers, the
Colombians, the Brazilians, the Mexicans
saying that they are 100% opposed to
American intervention.
What does that mean for American policy?
You know, we're not going to get any
help from any of the regional powers.
I just don't see what what how this
benefits the United States.
>> Yeah. I think there's a lot of talk
about how the US is starting to to harm
the relationship it has with Europe.
Now, I think there's a lot of um a lot
of substance in the criticism that the
US has been um sending Europe's way,
especially when it comes to free speech.
But now we're seeing the same thing
Latin America. If the US does conduct a
regime change operation, even enemies of
of Maduro won't be too happy to see that
happening to one of their neighbors, and
it could lead to a lot of immigration to
their country, a lot of instability in
their country. Um, so from a foreign
policy perspective, a regime change
long-term is in my opinion could erode
trust in the US as as an ally for all
these different countries. That's why
I'm hoping it is it is a bluff. But then
and there's also on a poly there's a a
platform called polyark where people
make a bet on certain outcomes and
people are betting two days ago they
were betting I think 50/50 that Maduro
is going to be leaving to Qatar. There's
been rumors about him planning to leave
to Qatar, but late recently he's been
upping the ante, immobilizing the
military. We saw that in the last two
days. Um, but there's one development
that surprised me is uh there's been
reports that Maduro was seeking amnesty
for the US for him to step down and
Trump refused to give him amnesty. Um,
if that is true, what's the strategic
reason not to provide Maduro with
amnesty?
The only thing that I could think of was
that Donald Trump wants a scalp. You
remember um there,
you remember that uh Manuel Morie, who
was the the president and and military
leader of Panama back during the George
HW Bush uh years. uh he was a long-term
paid asset [snorts] of the CIA until the
CIA just didn't need him anymore and
they turned on him and all of a sudden
he became an internationally wanted
narcotics trafficker which may or may
not have been true and even if it was
true the CIA knew he was doing it from
the beginning anyway. So, um,
we sent in a small strike force and and
kidnapped him and brought him back to
Miami and, uh, put him on trial for
international drug trafficking and he
was convicted and sentenced to life
without parole. I think he ended up
dying in a French prison or something
like that. We we allowed him to
transfer, but I'm thinking that this is
this is probably what the administration
wants. They want a scalp. They want some
somebody that they can point to to show
that they're serious about drugs and uh
and they prove that they're serious
about drugs by taking this narcotics
trafficker, which he's not, and giving
him a sentence of life without parole.
It's the only thing that I can think of.
Otherwise, it doesn't make any sense.
And let me add one other thing, too. One
of the things that I learned early on at
the CIA was that the United States is
really good at overthrowing governments.
It's not hard to do. The real work is
what you do after the government has
been overthrown. And we don't have the
foggiest idea how to bring stability to
these countries whose governments we
overthrow. Look at Iraq, look at
Afghanistan, look at Libya, look at
Syria, look at Sudan. You can Somalia.
You can look all over the world. And
finally, one other point.
the overthrow of the Arben's government
in Guatemala, the overthrow of it
doesn't even have to be Arbenz, it can
be any number of a dozen different
Central and South American countries may
have happened 75 years ago, but in the
minds of most Latin Americans, uh it it
happened yesterday.
And so there's this real distrust of the
United States when it comes to the issue
of overthrowing governments and allowing
chaos to ensue or allow military
dictatorships to to entrench themselves
in power. Nothing good comes from this
kind of US foreign policy.
>> I've been always critical of regime
changes, especially the mess that we've
seen in the Middle East. But I I thought
I'd I'd look into the issue with an open
mind to see if there's been successful
regime changes. I'm like maybe maybe the
US has had more successful regime
changes that I'm not aware of that
people don't talk about. I struggle to
find any when I consider something to be
successful one successful for the US
itself uh from a selfish perspective and
number two um does not lead to complete
failure of the state as we've seen in
Syria, Libya etc.
>> Most of the success stories were after
World War II so decades and decades ago
and recently in the 80s there's Panama
and Granada were labeled as successful
but that's about it. Um, so it doesn't,
you know,
it's hard to be optimistic looking at
that track record for the US and it and
and add that to the split we're seeing
with MAGA with Israel versus America
first with US involvement in Iran and
the Iran war with um the the the Ukraine
war is a different story. Um it just
makes it to it makes it a very difficult
a very not difficult very illogical
choice for Trump to take based on this
data. Let's go back to the reason that
Trump and his administration has given
and that's uh Venezuela being labeled as
a narco state. Not sure what that means.
Maybe you can explain it to us. Um I've
looked at the numbers. It didn't make
sense. The biggest producers of drugs,
Colombia, Mexico, Peru, Bolivia.
Venezuela is not even in the top five.
The biggest transit transit countries
for for flows of drugs, Mexico,
Honduras, Guatemala, Ecuador, Panama.
The only one that Venezuela was lodging
in in terms of transit was um coke
cocaine and but the majority of it is
for Europe. It's 24% transit uh through
Venezuela mostly to Europe only 8% to
the US which puts it below Mexico,
Honduras, Guatemala, Panama and Ecuador,
just above the Dominican Republic. So it
just shows that Venezuela is not really
that much of a narco state. Um but I I
do have a question though. Um, something
you've talked about recently on your
show is how the CIA used drugs as a way
to weaken other countries. They've done
it through Afghanistan to weaken Iran
and Russia. Is there a possibility that
China, maybe even Russia are using drug
flows from Latin America, maybe not
Venezuela based on those numbers, but
maybe other countries to weaken the US?
It because Trump has blamed China for
all of these flaws of of fentinel. Could
there be some some truth to that claim?
Yes, I would believe that. Um, friends
of mine at the DEA have said over the
years that, uh, that's why the fentinel
problem is as bad as it is here in the
United States. U, a lot of the fentinel
comes from from Mexico, of course, but
originates in China or the precursors
originate in China and are sent to
Mexico uh, to be manufactured there. But
yeah, um, the Chinese look, the Chinese
have the same calculation that the CIA
does. Uh we knew that that Afghanistan
was producing 93% of the world's heroin,
but that almost all of that heroin was
destined to for Russia and and Iran and
it weakened their societies. That's
better for us if they're weak. But the
Chinese come to the same calculation
that fentinyl flooding into the United
States weakens our society and that's
better for the Chinese. So sure, I could
see that I could see that as a long a
long-term Chinese policy.
but not like to Venezuela based on the
numbers I've just mentioned and you
mentioned early in the interview. Um,
all right. So, looking at Venezuela,
what's the strategy? Is it oil? You
talked about oil being very dirty. Is it
other natural reserves, natural gas,
iron ore, boxite, gold? Is it increasing
presence in of Chinese presence in the
region? You've talked about the Chinese
and and Indian oil refinery starting
about five years ago. Um, what is the
the the thinking behind the scenes in
Washington?
>> I think it's all of those things. I
think all of those things that you just
listed are part of the conversations
that are taking place at the White
House, the State Department, and the
Defense Department. And in addition to
that, Guyana just discovered in the last
3 years or so that they are sitting on
an ocean of oil. The Venezuelans say,
"No, that's our oil." And the
Venezuelans momentarily threatened the
uh the sanctity of of the border with
Guyana. The United States might be able
to use that as a pretext. Relations
between the US and Guyana are very good.
Uh, US oil companies are already there
uh, looking for and drilling for Gion
oil. So, it could be that as well.
>> All right, let's say they move ahead
with a regime change. John, um, Trump
did talk about authorizing the CIA,
which is a bit weird. He talked about it
publicly. I thought these things are
usually done behind the scenes. First
maybe give give us your exact I'm not
sure if that was the first time by
president. You're saying it is. Tell me
what was your reaction when you heard
that? Is that a way to threaten Maduro?
Is that why he said it? Does that mean
anything?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. He he he did that just to frighten
Maduro. Listen, at the CIA, there is
literally nothing that is more highly
classified than a covert action program.
You you're not even allowed to say the
words covert action program in public
when you're a CIA officer. So then you
have the president of the United States
getting up on national television and
saying he's just authorized a covert
action program to overthrow the the
Venezuelan government. First of all, I I
don't know if that's true. He may have
just said that to frighten Maduro, or he
may have actually done it, but again, I
I'll repeat myself. Uh what would that
entail? It would entail a handful of
people. um no more than I don't know a
few hundred a thousand at the maximum
and they would have to take over the
presidential palace or force Maduro out
um pacify the military which is
impossible at this early stage because
the military supports Maduro. It always
has uh take over the radio and
television stations in the capital and
control the major intersections in the
capital. First of all, we we're not even
sure that that's all possible as part of
a covert action program. You would
probably need troops on the ground from
the defense department. But secondly,
what do you do 24 hours later? Let's say
Maduro does run off to wherever he's
going to run off to. Then what do you
do? Again, this was a lesson that I
learned at the CIA. There's never a plan
for day two. The planning only is about
day one. What are your thoughts on his
uh on the main opposition leader, Maria
Machado?
>> I I don't think she's any more than Juan
Guaido was. The the right-wing
opposition is is um divided. It's always
been divided. Um Maria Machado may have
won the Nobel Peace Prize, but it's my
understanding that she's no more popular
than any other right-wing political
figure. Uh, Juan Guyaido, it's funny, we
we coerced something like 36 countries
into into um recognizing Juan Guyaido as
the president of Venezuela. In fact, he
was just a graduate student here at
George Washington University in
Washington DC. Uh, never had access to
Venezuela.
And then there's there's a there's a
stipulation in the Venezuelan contra um
contract. There's a stipulation in the
Venezuelan constitution saying that if
the president can't assume the
presidency within 30 days of taking the
oath of office, then he no longer
continues to be the president. And
apparently at the White House, nobody
bothered to read the Venezuelan
constitution because Juan Guaido never
left Washington.
>> Well, with Maria Machado, I just she
doesn't command armies, she doesn't
command troops. I just don't see her
turning into anything there. I would I
if in the event that that Maduro leaves,
I would look for the next leader to be a
senior military officer.
>> Interesting. Um so let's going back to
to the original question, if they do go
ahead with a coup, the first step would
be to take out Maduro. Is that would
that be to capture him? Cuz it's not
like it's not going to be a surprise
coup. There's been so many warnings.
There's been a military buildup. So
Madura is obviously ready and preparing
for this. makes it very difficult to
conduct a coup when you talk openly
about a covert um action program. Uh but
let's say considering the circumstances
that we have now, how would they take
him out? Would a would a military strike
similar to what we saw a decapitation
strike like what Israel done in Iran,
could that work in Venezuela?
>> Cuz you're talking about a sitting
president of a country. You're breaking
so many rules. You're you're shaking up
a system that allowed the US to flourish
over the last few decades. you just
keep, you know, chipping away at that
system that the US built since World War
II.
>> Yeah. We we have to remember this is an
internationally recognized president of
a sovereign nation. This is not
something that should be considered
lightly. Um
>> and not in a time of war either
>> and right and
>> Iran was Iran was funding milit you can
criticize or support Iran but they were
militarily funding enemies of Israel. So
it's a very different circumstance. And
when Israel struck Iranian leaders, a
lot of people criticized Israel's
action. When Israel struck Yemeni
leaders, the leadership there, they
killed a whole bunch of them in in one
strike. A lot of people were critical of
Israel's actions. But Yemen was striking
Israel. In this case, you've got Maduro
asking Trump allegedly for amnesty and
potentially wanting to step down, but
not declaring any war, direct or
indirect, on the US. It's very different
circumstances.
>> Very different. there there's nothing
that's that's
that falls on the side of the United
States here. Maduro is the
internationally recognized president.
The United States and Venezuela are not
in a state of war. To the best of my
knowledge, there are no criminal charges
yet pending against uh Maduro. I know
that something was introduced in New
York the other day, but I I don't know
if it's been if it's gone to a grand
jury yet. Um,
none of the regional powers support an
action against Maduro.
>> Europe doesn't either.
>> And Europe doesn't either. So the US
>> So what would be what are the options?
What are the options available for
regime change? How would they be able to
remove Maduro?
>> I think that they would have to allow
him to leave. Allow him safe passage
somewhere. Doha, Moscow,
Havana, somewhere. Just let him go. Mhm.
>> And then if that's the case though, what
do you make of the buildup as well? The
12 warships, the 15,000 troops. You
talked about a possibility of a ground
invasion. If you look at historically
other other regime change operations by
the US, how many involved such a a large
military presence as we're seeing here?
And um what would that military presence
military operation look like? Do you do
you expect US troops in Venezuela?
Because I don't expect most Americans
don't support that. I think it's above
70%. don't support any military
intervention there.
>> No, I I can't imagine that we would get
to that point. I can't imagine it. But
looking back at previous interventions,
we we had six carrier battle groups in
the uh in the Persian Gulf and one in
the Eastern Mediterranean uh to push the
Iraqis out of Kuwait. We had four
aircraft carrier battle groups for the
uh in the invasion of Kuwait in 2002. We
had four carrier battle groups in the
region to attack um uh Afghanistan in
2001. We have this one carrier battle
group
>> but
>> not enough for a whole
>> not enough operation.
>> Not enough for
>> especially for such a large country.
Venezuela is a massive country very
mountainous country as well.
>> Mountain and jungle. Mhm. The last
question, two questions I have for you
is um so if the US does succeed, if we
see one of those rare successful regime
changes, you said there's never a plan,
not a plan B, but a a a postre change
plan.
>> Um so then what would that look like?
Especially looking at history and how
other regime changes have gone. What do
you expect to happen in Venezuela if
Maduro does step down? I I think that we
would see a a period of chaos and in the
in the end I think I I believe strongly
that the military would uh would finally
take power. Maybe not permanently but it
would be a military
>> transitional government.
>> Yeah. Transitional government. I I want
to make a comparison to Libya if I
could. Mario,
>> please. uh when
the US and NATO overthrew uh Muamar
Gaddafi back in the uh during the the
Obama administration.
I happened to be invited to and and
listen to how awful this is. I happened
to be invited to the unveiling of the
new Libyan Constitution.
It was unveiled at a at a lobbying firm
here in Washington DC. Right. So, a
group of wealthy Libyan exiles paid this
lobbying firm and said, "Write us a new
constitution." This constitution was
better than ours. It called for equal
rights for everybody, women, gays, LGBT,
whatever. Everybody was equal. They're
going to share the oil money. Incredible
constitution.
Did anybody ever do anything with it? Of
course not, because nobody ever heard of
these people in Washington DC and nobody
even wanted to read their silly
constitution. Instead, we've had a
period of what 15 16 years of fighting
and civil war and chaos and death. And
so the United States might think that
it's the good guy all the time. The
United States might think that it can
impose a peace on a country like
Venezuela. And it never works out that
way. It never works out the way the
policy makers think it's going to work
out. I remember, and I think I've told
you this before, I remember
participating in a in a classified video
teleconference the night before we
attacked Iraq in 2003, February of 2003,
and one of the participants at the
National Security Council said as we
were getting up to walk out, he said,
"Tomorrow morning when we cross the
border, the Iraqis are going to throw
flowers at us." And when I got back to
my office, I said to my boss, "Do these
people know nothing about history?" and
he said, "No, they know nothing about
history and nothing's changed between
2003 and 2025."
That is so like this is what perplexes
me the most, John. Like, you those
people I at least I believe they're
intelligent people running all these
different organizations. So, I don't
understand how those people that I'm
sure studied history, they know, I'm
sure maybe they're even watching you
this video, other videos you've done,
they understand that coups don't work.
>> Mhm. [clears throat] That's why I
struggle to see the the the thought
process, the the the logic behind making
decisions if a regime change is being
planned in Venezuela now. Like, how did
the people in Iraq expected flowers,
sorry, the people that that decided to
to to change regimes in Iraq and and
have the troops walk into the country?
How did they expect to have flowers
thrown into foreign troops walking into
a sovereign country? It's it's weird.
>> Yeah.
>> Who are those people?
>> I I can I can explain that. Um, in part,
number one, they think they're smarter
than you are, smarter than everybody
else in the room. Number two, back in
2003, it would have worked if they were
in charge, but the people in 2003, they
didn't know what they were talking
about. But today, I'm smarter and I know
more and I have more experience, so I'll
get it right this time. And uh, and
number three,
at least in the Middle East, you've got
this this voice on your shoulder saying,
"Attack Iran. attack Iraq, attack Iran,
attack Iraq. And it gets hard to say no
after a while, depending on who's the
president.
>> They're talking now about umah doing
business with Venezuela, working
directly with Venezuela. Suddenly in the
discussion, Venezuela is working
directly with Hzbalah and Iran and this
network and a new access of evil. Um
look, fingers crossed we don't see
another Libya here. It would be
heartbreaking for for the country of
Venezuela. But John, always an absolute
pleasure to speak to you. Thank you,
sir.
>> Pleasure is mine. And good to see you
again, Mario.